Guide to the Irvin D. Yalom Papers SC0598
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Irvin D. Yalom papers
1959-2015
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Yalom, Irvin D.
SC0598
24.25 Linear Feet 35 boxes
This collection contains both papers and books. The papers constitute the smaller portion of the collection and include miscellaneous notes; proposal for a bereavement study; correspondence, largely letters received, 1971-2008; draft of his article on Hemingway and a letter from C. T. Lanham regarding it, 1967; a lecture; articles and clippings; and programs from his public presentations. The books include both English and foreign language editions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Irvin D. Yalom, 2000-2015.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Irvin D. Yalom is Professor of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences, Emeritus, at Stanford University.
Description of the Collection
This collection contains both papers and books. The papers constitute the smaller portion of the collection and include miscellaneous notes; proposal for a bereavement study; correspondence, largely letters received, 1971-2008; draft of his article on Hemingway and a letter from C. T. Lanham regarding it, 1967; a lecture; articles and clippings; and programs from his public presentations. The books include both English and foreign language editions.
Group psychotherapy; Bereavement -- Psychological aspects.; Yalom, Irvin D.; Yalom, Irvin D.; Yalom, Irvin D.; Lanham, C. T. (Charles Trueman); Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1960
- Papers
  - Notes for book [unspecified title] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes for bereavement study (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Group III observer notes (Irv – Sunday) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Weekend Experience Study, General Impressions by Gary Bond, May 31, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - After the Patient Dies: A Study of Bereavement, 1985-87 (correspondence, budget materials, some notes) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bellagio Center, 1986-87 (correspondence and bereavement project description) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Supervision for Nick Ney's alcohol group, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Workshop invitations, 1986-89 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Signed permissions (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Sept.-October, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego (typescript article) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lecture, "The Hypnotic Relationship and Interpersonal Honesty," 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Publications with articles by Yalom, 1959-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Articles (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Articles (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reviews and articles (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Programs, announcements, and brochures from public presentations, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Books by Yalom: (Box 3)
    - Lying on the Couch (in English, Hebrew) (Box 3)
    - When Nietzsche Wept (in Hebrew, German, English, Danish, Finnish, Turkish, Romanian, Czech) (Box 3)
    - Love's Executioner (in German, Finnish, Danish, French, Swedish, English, Italian) (Box 3)
    - Everyday Gets a Little Closer; a Twice-Told Therapy (in German, Italian) (Box 3)
    - Theory and Practice of Group Psychotherapy (in German, English) (Box 3)
  - Books by Yalom: (Box 4)
    - Lying on the Couch (in Turkish, German, Norwegian, Spanish, Danish, English) (Box 4)
    - Mama and the Meaning of Life (in English, Spanish, Norwegian) (Box 4)
    - Inpatient Group Psychotherapy (in Turkish, English) (Box 4)
    - The Yalom Reader (in Spanish, English) (Box 4)
  - Others: (Box 4)
    - Current Psychotherapies, ed. Raymond J. Corsini and Danny Wedding, with chapter by Yalom (Box 4)
    - Volumes in the Jossey-Bass Library of Current Clinical Technique (Irvin D. Yalom, general editor) (Box 4)
  - Books by Yalom: (Box 5)
    - Everyday Gets a Little Closer; a Twice-Told Therapy (in Turkish, Hebrew, Spanish) (Box 5)
    - Love's Executioner (in English) (Box 5)
    - Existential Psychotherapy (in German, Turkish, Spanish, Danish) (Box 5)
    - Theory and Practice of Group Psychotherapy (in Italian, [Slavic language], German, Spanish) (Box 5)
    - Encounter Groups: First Facts (in English) (Box 5)
  - Books by Yalom: (Box 6)
    - When Nietzsche Wept (in Portuguese, Danish, Spanish, German, Italian) (Box 6)
    - Love's Executioner (in Chinese, Hebrew, Polish, English, Japanese, Spanish) (Box 6)
    - Love's Executioner (audio book, read by Yalom) (Box 6)
    - Existential Psychotherapy (in English) (Box 6)
    - Everyday Gets a Little Closer; a Twice-Told Therapy (in English) (Box 6)
    - Video tapes (14) of group sessions (Box 6)
    - Video tape of Yalom reading from Lying on the Couch at Border's Bookstore in San Francisco, 1996 (Box 6)
  - unspecified
    General note
    Collection also includes two boxes of restricted files, mostly transcripts from therapy sessions.
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2001-136
  - Clippings, 1970-99 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Email printouts, June 1998-June 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Email printouts, August 2000-March 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Introduction Carl Rogers' book A Way of Being [photocopy], 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invitation to teach at University of Rochester, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1952-ca. 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reprint, "The Use of Small Interactional Groups in the Teaching of Psychiatry", 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Syllabus, "Death in Literature and Psychology," taught by Irvin and Marilyn Yalom, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Inside Therapy [advance uncorrected proofs] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Love's Executioner (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Momma and the Meaning of Life (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Treating Adolescents [Yalom was general editor for the series] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Readings in Existential Psychology & Psychiatry [no article by Yalom] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Contains translations of The Yalom Reader, Love's Executioner, Lying on the Couch, Momma and the Meaning of Life, and When Nietzsche Wept (Box 2)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2002-076
  - Anderson, Lorraine, "Author Insight: Irvin D. Yalom," 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles and reviews (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles and reviews (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificates (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Group Psychotherapy Convention, Jamaica, 1984 – itinerary (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hemingway – draft of article (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hemingway – letter from C. T. Lanham, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Inpatient Group Therapy – correspondence regarding the book, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters received from readers, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1971-78 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous reviews of Yalom's books, typescript copies (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Personal Histories" – rejection letters, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Roth, Jeff, "The Compatibility of Two Theories of Depression: Beck's Cognitive Model and Yalom's Existential Model," student paper, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rubin, Simon Shimshon, "Ethical Dilemmas, Good Intentions, and the Road to Hell: A Clinical-Ethical Perspective on Yalom's Depiction of Trotter's Therapy," ca. 2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Workshops, classes, etc., – programs, 1974-81 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Workshops, classes, etc., – programs, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Workshops, classes, etc., – programs, 1983-84 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Workshops, classes, etc., – programs, 1985-86, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Workshop evaluation, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Workshops, correspondence regarding, 1983-85 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Workshops – Evaluation Research Associates, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Galleys for Greek edition of When Nietzsche Wept (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2004-047
    - Correspondence, March – August 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Sept. – Oct. 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Jan. – April 2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, June – Sept. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Oct. – Dec. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Jan. – Feb. 2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Book info (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Programs: Mastering Counseling Skills, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Clippings and articles (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Photograph, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Yalom, Eksistentiel psykoterapi [Danish translation of The Gift of Therapy] (Box 1)
    - Yalom, Terapiens essens [Danish translation] (Box 1)
    - Yalom, [Greek translation of Love's Executioner] (Box 1)
    - Yalom, Und Nietzsche Weinte (Box 2)
    - Yalom & Elkin, Jeden Tag ein bibschen naher (Box 2)
    - Yalom, [Russian translation of Momma and the Meaning of Life] (Box 2)
    - Yalom, El don de la terapia [Spanish translation of The Gift of Therapy] (Box 2)
    - Yalom, The Gift of Therapy (Box 2)
    - Yalom, [Japanese or Chinese translation of The Gift of Therapy] (Box 2)
    - Yalom, Bagislanan Terapi [translation of The Gift of Therapy] (Box 2)
    - Yalom, Chvala psychoterapie [Yugoslavian translation of The Gift of Therapy] (Box 2)
    - Yalom, Terapins gava [Danish translation of The Gift of Therapy] (Box 2)
    - Yalom, [Greek translation of Religion and Psychiatry] (Box 2)
    - Yalom, Terapiens gave [Swedish translation of The Gift of Therapy] (Box 2)
    - Yalom, Terapiens essens [Danish translation of The Gift of Therapy] 2nd copy (Box 2)
    - Yalom, [Greek translation of Lying on the Couch] (Box 2)
    - Yalom, [Hebrew translation of Momma and the Meaning of Life] (Box 2)
  - Audio Tapes:
    - Evolution of Psychotherapy, "The Therapists use of Self: How Nietzche Might Have Invented Psychotherapy," Hamburg, July 1994 (Box 1)
    - Evolution of Psychotherapy, conversation hour, Hamburg, July 1994 (Box 1)
    - Excerpts from Momma and the Meaning of Life, read by Irvin D. Yalom (Box 1)
  - Books:
    - Momma and the Meaning of Life [Swedish translation 1999] (Box 1)
    - Theorie und Praxis der Gruppenpsychotherapie (Box 1)
    - The Gift of Therapy; an Open Letter to a New Generation of Therapists and Their Patients [uncorrected proof 2002] (Box 1)
    - The Gift of Therapy; an Open Letter to a New Generation of Therapists and Their Patients [German translation 2002] (Box 1)
    - When Nietzsche Wept [Greek translation 2001] (Box 1)
    - When Nietzsche Wept [Russian translation] (Box 1)
    - Theory and Practice of Group Psychotherapy [Chinese translation 2001] (Box 1)
    - Inpatient Group Psychotherapy [Chinese translation 2001] (Box 1)
    - Yalom and Elkin, Every Day Gets a Little Closer; a Twice-Told Therapy [German translation 2001] (Box 1)
    - Breuer and Freud, Studies on Hysteria. The definitive edition with a new forward by Irvin D. Yalom. 2000 (Box 1)
    - Salgado, Susana, Y el Papa Lloro, en Recoleta. Buenos Aires, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, copies of letters, programs, and other items pertaining to Yalom's work and writings, 1970-84, with emphasis on encounter groups (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mounted ad for Lying on the Couch (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2005-352
  - Catalog, Harper Collins (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (received), 003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence (received), 2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Lettre ouverte à une nouvelle génération de psychothéerapeutes et à leurs patients" – typescript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reviews, articles, etc. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Foreign editions of The Schopenhauer Cure, Lying on the Couch and The Gift of Therapy (Box 2)
  - Foreign editions of Love's Executioner, The Yalom Reader, Existential Psychotherapy, and When Nietzsche Wept, and the 2003 English paperback edition of When Nietzsche Wept (Box 3)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2006-172
  - Articles about Yalom, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ABC Radio National, "The Schopenhauer Cure", 2005; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificate, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings and announcements of appearances, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Translations of his books: The Schopenhauer Cure, Religion and Psychiatry, Lying on the Couch, Love's Executioner, and When Nietzsche Wept (Box 2)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2007-146
  - Boston University School of Medicine, Class of 1956 Fiftieth Reunion Newsletter, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Email 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Email Jan.-June 2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Foreign language press (Portuguese) on play based on Yalom's When Nietzsche Wept, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invitation to Yalom's talk at Turning Point of Tampa, Sept. 18, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters 2006-07 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Program from Berkeley Public Library Foundation's Authors Dinner (features quote from Yalom book), 2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reviews of the German edition of The Schopenhauer Cure, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Yalom in American magazine 2006-07 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Yalom in foreign language magazines 2006-07 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Foreign language translations of Yalom's books (Box 2)
  - Oversized magazine in Portuguese (Revista) with interview of Yalom 2006 (Box 2 os)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2007-188
  - Correspondence received 2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Yalom, "Afterword," ca. 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cable guide to "El dia que Nietzsche lloro" (Box 1)
  - Russian translation of The Schopenhauer Cure (Box 1)
  - Greek translation of Momma and the Meaning of Life (Box 1)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2007-329
  - Two folders of email, letters, reviews, advertisements, flyers, 1993-2007; and two foreign magazines, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Translations of his books: The Theory and Practice of Group Psychotherapy, Momma and the Meaning of Life, The Gift of Therapy, Love's Executioner, and Existential Psychotherapy (Box 2)
  - Four award certificates/plaques 1979-2005 (Box 2)
  - Two posters (not in English) (Box 2)
  - Mounted poster [bookstore display?] about his book Lying on the Couch (Box 3)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2008-035
  - Understanding Group Psychotherapy with Irvin Yalom, M.D. Volume I: Outpatients (psychotherapy.net, 2006) 2 DVD set with instructor's manual (Box 1)
  - Understanding Group Psychotherapy with Irvin Yalom, M.D. Volume II: Inpatients (psychotherapy.net, 2006) 2 DVD set with instructor's manual (Box 1)
  - Understanding Group Psychotherapy with Irvin Yalom, M.D. Volume III: An Interview (psychotherapy.net, 2006) with instructor's manual [1 DVD] (Box 1)
  - The Gift of Therapy, A Conversation with Irvin Yalom, M.D. (psychotherapy.net, 2006) with instructor's manual [1 DVD] (Box 1)
  - Irvin Yalom: Live Case Consultation (psychotherapy.net, 2006) with instructor's manual [1 DVD] (Box 1)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2009-197
  - Letters and email, 2007-2008 (Box 1)
  - Responses from participants at Yalom workshop, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Introduction to Yalom by Fotini Tsalikoglou (Athens), May 2005 (Box 1)
  - Facebook print-out (Irvin D. Yalom Fans), April 2008 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous items (including book review, notices, conference program) (Box 1)
  - Irvin Yalom: Live Case Consultation (Psychotherapy.net) with instructor's manual, 2005; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd) (Box 1)
  - Magazines, clippings, and other examples of press coverage (Box 1)
  - Hardback copy of his book Staring at the Sun (Box 1)
  - Paperback copies of Staring at the Sun and On Psychotherapy and the Human Condition (Box 2)
  - Translations of his books: Love's Executioner, The Schopenhauer Cure, Theory and Practice of Group Psychotherapy, Staring at the Sun, Momma and the Meaning of Life, Every Day Gets a Little Closer, Existential Psychotherapy, and Religion or Psychotherapy [possibly a translation of a journal article] (Box 2)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2010-005
  - Ads, programs, announcements (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Psychiatric Association 162nd Annual Meeting program, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, articles from the Internet (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Email, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters received, 2008-09 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reviews of Yalom's books (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tieche, Gary, screenplay of Lying on the Couch, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Magazines with Yalom interviews and articles (Box 2)
  - Yalom, The Gift of Therapy, Harper paperback edition 2009 (Box 2)
  - Foreign translations of: The Schopenhauer Cure, Staring at the Sun, I'm Calling the Police – A Tale of Repression and Recovery, Love's Executioner, Religion and Psychiatry, Lying on the Couch, Existential Psychotherapy, Theory and Practice of Group Psychotherapy, When Nietzsche Wept, and Every Day Gets a Little Closer (Box 2)
- Additional Papers, 1973-2011; Accession ARCH-2011-537
  - Articles re: Yalom, 2006, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2009-2011 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1973, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Those We Are" documentary project (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Papers, 2011-2012; Accession ARCH-2013-013
  - Printed email correspondence, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book reviews, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Spinoza Problem," Jewish Public Library, Montreal, Canada, 2012 May 23; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd) (Box 2)
  - "The antennas of our time", 1 optical disc(s) (dvd) (Box 3)
  - Interview on Paris TV, "Les Mots du Minuit", 2012 Jun; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd) (Box 4)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2015-001
  - Incoming Letters, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incoming Letters, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Incoming Letters, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Incoming Letters, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Incoming Letters, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Incoming Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Theodore Roosevelt High School Rough Rider class of 1949 reunion, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Illinois Group Psychotherapy Society workshop with Yalom, 1984 Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Buchkultur featuring article about Yalom, 2012 Aug/Sept (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Yalom as teacher, mentor and friend. The National Psychologist., 2013 Nov/Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ich hatte so viel Gluck im Leben. Psychologies., 2014 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tales of sound and fury: healing the angry and those who hurt. Symposium at Cantor., 2014 Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Love, literature and marriage. Event at Pen American Center West., 2014 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Shopenhauer Cure, film adaptations (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - KQED Forum with Yalom, 2002 Mar 7; 1.1; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Conferences/Events, 2013-2015 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 2012-2015 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters and cards, 1978-2015 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Email correspondence, 2012-2013 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Email correspondence, 2014-2015 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - How I Write - Irvin Yalom, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Additional Papers, 1963-2014; ARCH-2015-033
  - California Book Awards, 1993; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Love's Executioner and Other Tales of Psychotherapy, 2013; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1)
  - Awards, 1963, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1968, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Press, 1990-2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2017-190
  - Correspondence with publishers, 2015-2015 (Box 1)